hi welcome back to negotiator part three
and we've reached chapter 15
uh which is called an investigation of a
nature to things in tibetan we can see
here
it's called rangin thakba okay
[Music]
an investigation
rang shin is an interesting word because
it means its own face
shin hue means face
which means face
so rang shin means the face of something
which means
it's nature which means and get it
straight at the beginning okay
it means the identity of something okay
the inherent
nature some quality of a thing
which is inside of it so you gotta get
this feeling of
we're gonna investigate whether or not
for example fire
has an identity or a nature inside of it
of being hot and then that nature kind
of
opens up and expresses itself in the
world you know does fire have a
nature inside of it which is hot
and then somehow the fire opens up and
the hotness comes out you know it's it
doesn't have its own
identity so when we say nature here
or swabala uh ranchin
think about
it's sort of a thing deep down inside of
a thing which is its true identity think
of identity okay
all right here we go to our arguments
uh
first birth
first person
canada country relationship
if you think about it
if something's identity is part of it
it shouldn't have to be created
if if the identity of an object
is inherent to it
which is what identity means
it shouldn't be something that you get
only if something else happens
okay you're just born with it you know
you just come with it you know nobody
has to heat up a fire
so if it were the case that you had to
do something to make the fire hot
then hot wouldn't be the nature of fire
okay
are we agreeing
yeah if if you had to do something else
if you had to light a fire under a fire
to make it hot
then the nature of the fire we wouldn't
say hot as the nature of the fire so we
can say something about
nature or identity it comes with the
thing and it's not something that comes
about if other things are there if other
causes and conditions are there okay
it would be improper to say that
something's
self-identity
were only there if something else
happened some kinds of causes and
conditions
because a nature which was produced by
other factors and other causes
would be artificial
and artificial is the opposite of nature
okay it would be
put together and and given to the fire
okay oh here let me heat you up
you know and then the fire gets hot you
know then the nature
wouldn't be the nature in the fire
it would be produced artificially and
handed to the fire okay got it
all right
so chen here
means
almost artificial created
okay
in in the jewelry business they have uh
real
rubies and sapphires and then they have
fake ones
but when they learned how to make real
ruby and sapphire in a laboratory
they had a big debate about whether to
call it artificial or not and the guys
have succeeded in the process and it's
not artificial it's real
and then the other guy said it's not
real if you don't dig it out of the
earth
so they made a compromise and they
called it created
ruby
and uh it sounds better right than
artificial
or substitute
[Music]
so
if it's created it's not natural that's
the point okay that's telling you
uh wrong
if the
self nature of a thing or if the
identity everything has to be created
from the outside
cheetah
then how the hell can you call it a
nature
it's artificial it's created okay got it
like created rubies
all right nagarjuna
now this is a story this picture has a
story okay so my llama i told you i was
a volunteer for my teacher
in uh for 30 years okay and about 25 of
those years
i was his
chauffeur
from new jersey to washington dc it's a
five hour drive
and he used to teach there once a month
so i did that drive
over 300 times
okay i drove him down there if you count
both ways 600 times okay and so i knew
all the road by by heart and i enjoyed
driving him because he would always
refuse to answer my questions
and in the car he couldn't refuse
he was locked in the car for five hours
and uh
and he ordered the car without a radio
so i couldn't listen to the radio
and it cost extra money to order the car
without the radio
so anyway all we had to do was talk
about dharma
and then sometimes he would pretend to
be asleep and i know you know
anyway
we used to always stop at a howard
johnson's uh
at the maryland border delaware border
uh just before the delray bridge and
we'd always stop at the same place
and he would order his tea
and you know he's a big tea drinker he
drove he drank about 15 cups of tea a
day i made him 15 20 cups of tea a day
and
they would try to give him creamer
you know and he'd say no i want cream
this is creamer i don't want creamer i
want cream you know i want the real
thing and he taught me all these words
for artificial fake not natural
this is
all the words i learned from him which
were all my words
they have our contacts we were sitting
somewhere and he said this is called
chima
chama means chipper chipper means it had
to be created from the outside it's not
natural okay
all right so
and he hated this stuff
uh
dearly all right okay
next verse it's actually half a birth
and this is actually wrong luke so
what's that mean
this is our position okay
if something was a real
identity
it shouldn't be
means contrived
or artificially created
it shouldn't be like the creamer okay it
should just be real
chu min means not
not created what's a famous
chipper in lamrim
chamomile uh that's where you try to
feel like a bodhisattva
when you're not and that's a good german
okay
all right fake bodhisattva
[Music]
created bodhisattva
artificial but you pretend to be a
buddhist officer and then you still
you're messing up all day and stuff like
that okay
if something were a true nature
it shouldn't have to depend on any
conditions going around outside of it
okay if fire is hot
by nature
it it shouldn't matter where the fire is
or where the what's happening with the
fire it should be hot from the inside
something
that's our definition of a nature
and i was wondering and maybe you guys
could think it over
is this
thakpatasumgirikpa is this tarpatasson
and that's a very very useful expression
i remember where i i was in a debate one
day in uh
jaipur monastery and i heard this word
means
theoretical argument theoretical case in
the theoretical case that something had
a self-nature
it should have these two qualities what
chu min it shouldn't be artificially
created and it should be shen locked up
it should not
rely on other conditions okay
so
can such a nature exist
that's another debate got it so in
theory we say in theory right
in theory this is what a self-nature
would be you know in practice is there
such a thing
[Music]
and and
choni lama also
expresses his opinion
and this is a very traditional ancient
opinion on what a self nature would look
like if it existed and it should have
three qualities okay here we go
number one
is a very very
rare important word that means
from the beginning
it sounds like
meaning a
bamboo shoot but it's not lukma means
primeval
primordial
since forever okay
no
it
if if
if something is the nature of fire
it should have been in fires since
forever
okay meaning heart he okay if something
is the
if fire has a nature
then a self nature or an identity
then it should have always been in those
things as long as fires were ever ever
were
that's the first thing okay fire should
have been hot since forever
number two
no matter
whether you're talking about a fire 100
years ago or a fire 100 years from now
or a fire in this room right now
it should be invariable
the identity should always be there okay
whether you're talking about
fire 100 years from now or 500 years ago
or fire in this present instant
uh that identity should always be there
for heart
number three
uh
it should not be
uh dependent on other sources
for its identity okay and he gives an
interesting example
you don't have to put a hot water bottle
on a fire
me and veronica we have this cool thing
down there somebody gave a
it's a cherry pit
in a bag
and it has lavender uh flowers in there
and you put it in the microwave and you
heat it up
and then you lie down on it it's very
pleasant when you go to bed for it stays
warm for like half an hour or something
and then it slowly gets cooler and you
fall asleep but it's very pleasant so
that's kind of like a hot water bottle
okay
so he says
you if
if fire is hot from inside and you don't
have to
warm up the fire with a hot water bottle
or the bite it's a bunny with the cherry
pits and lavender inside of it
if you don't need a cherry pit lavender
bunny heat up in the microwave to make
you warm you are probably warm by nature
got it
okay those are the three requirements
and again it's probably tapatas
here's a woman uh touching a candle
flame
and you know one thing you can say about
the
one thing you automatically think is i
hope she didn't put her finger in it
because it would burn her okay its
nature is to be hot
all right next verse
this is some kind of
[Music]
other ideas about identity if
you know my main thing about identity is
those three ideas
but let's talk about some other things
let's talk about some other
characteristics of the concept of
identity
this is very complex
if you think about it
fire has two natures
one is
inherent and one is adventitious
it's color for example
me adventitious means
it depends on outside circumstances okay
so like which chemical did you
what chemicals are in the wood
will make a different color of flame but
the heat is there
the heater is the identity of fire
and the color is
secondary it's a secondary
characteristic the secondary
characteristics of fire can be created
by other forces
the self-identity of fire should come
from the inside
so
if nobody made a fire hot
but you can change the color by
sprinkling different chemicals in it
okay so
and
everything about the fire is contained
in those two things either
it's natural identity
or it's a characteristic which is
imparted by other circumstances like
it's color okay
uh schengen mobile and there's nothing
else about fire
shanking
uh
what you call a nature that comes
from somewhere else
when the other person thinks of a nature
we would say
you're talking about a self-existent
somewhere else
what do you mean
does the color of the fire depend on an
outside source yes
but when you say that
you think the chemicals made the color
got it
did the color of the fire is the color
of the fire part of its
natural identity no it can change
according to chemicals
if you put sprinkle chemicals on a fire
and it changes the color of the fire
that's adventitious that's you know
secondary that's created by outside
forces okay
but but when you when you hear me say
that
you think it comes from the chemicals
and that's a problem
you're even messing up the secondary
ones
okay forget that forget that the fire is
hot from its own side which it's not
it's hot from your side
but forget that supposed identity
you even misunderstand why it changes
color you think it's the chemicals
okay got it
and there's nothing else about the fire
by the way
that's all there is there's what it is
and there's the stuff it could be
and you don't understand either one
okay
there's no other fire
than the one
which is its natural identity combined
with its other
characteristics that are created by
other forces there's no other fire than
that okay
once you cover those two that's the
whole fire and you don't understand
either one therefore you don't
understand the fire
all right
anyway
and here's where he says you know you
don't understand the language
and you don't understand the shang
you don't understand the basic nature of
the fire
it's own self nature and you don't
understand why it why it's moving or why
it has different colors or stuff or why
it's different temperature you don't
notice
if the
identity of the fire and the
characteristics of the fire
exist the way you think they do it
couldn't be a fire
killing upon madrid
if there was no real fire
men do by mean girl
then you couldn't have
the concept of unreal
okay if there's no real fire
then it's difficult to define unreal if
there's no real cream on the table
there's no it's difficult for my teacher
to say
that's fake cream the powder is fake
cream if if he's never seen the real
cream
he can't
the real cream defines the fake cream
and the fake cream defines the real
cream and you don't he doesn't smile
and say ah real cream
if he never had the danger of having
fake cream
you get it okay
and it was always my job to talk to
the waitress and giving him real cream
oh my god sometimes that took half an
hour
okay
when something changes into something
else we already talked about it when
milk for example
transforms into yogurt
means people say people in the world say
what mom means people in the world say
then what did they say it's not what it
used to be
when milk changes into yogurt
how do people talk about the milk
they said well it's not
what it used to be now it's all
hunky and before it was fluid
you know
and if you could say about a thing that
it used to be then it doesn't have a
nature
that's not what it used to be
it's not what it used to be
means whatever changed wasn't inherent
was not its identity
the milk
the
when i look at the yogurt i say the milk
there's not it's not milk anymore when
you say it's not milk anymore you're
saying something about the identity of
milk you're saying that it can end
you're saying that it can drop its
identity then it's not inherent is it
then it must be coming from somewhere
else right then it doesn't have an
inherent identity all it has is these
other characteristics that are created
by outside forces such as your feet in
your mind
got it
okay
then the picture is a real cream
and i i always see my teacher smiling
when i look at the real question
[Music]
all right
uh
let's go to the next verse
this is this typical
means
its identity its natural identity
means it's additional characteristics
added on by other circumstances okay
[Music]
is it fake or is it real
okay is it
real cream
or is it creamer okay
is it something made from a cow that
tastes delicious
or
is it something
created by powder okay so he's making
two
two sets of distinctions here
uh
its identity and its extra
characteristics that are variable
and then
uh
the real milk and the fake note okay two
sets of differences two differences okay
two sets of differences
when i describe them to you nagarjuna
talking to the other guy you still think
they're all self-existent
okay when i say real or unreal
and by the way i'll ask you a question
is it true that real can only be defined
by the unreal
is it true that identity
natural identity can only be defined by
characteristics which come and go
is it true that you have to see
short to perceive tall
in buddhism
because because a lot of people will
tell you
and i see this all the time there's some
burmese school or something in america
they're always talking about uh
emptiness as meaning
uh the result of comparison
that nothing is real by itself because
it has to be compared to something else
is that
emptiness is that dependent on solution
it's not okay it has nothing to do with
it
okay that whole explanation emptiness is
ridiculous
tall is not defined by short tall is
defined by the seeds we're tall in your
mind
that's all
you can have tall without shoring
because you can have seats for tall in
your mind without short okay
if tall doesn't depend on short tall
depends on what you did yesterday to
somebody
okay got it
things aren't what they are by
comparison
realism real is not defined by
artificial
in in buddhism
in real buddhism
and uh
identity is not defined by temporary
coming and going characteristics okay
identity is defined
by your seeds okay
all right uh they know
if you think
uh big is only big by comparison
or identity is only identity by
comparison to
adventitious or coming and going
characteristics
people who say that they don't
yeah they didn't see emptiness
they shouldn't you know such this they
didn't touch what means
here
okay if you think
things are only what they are by
comparison in a way
then you're thinking that identity comes
from its own side
or identity comes from the side of
comparison
and then you don't understand
the nature of things
it's a joke get it
you don't understand the nature the real
nature of things they need
you know the real nature of things it's
a joke
okay
by the way uh as taught in the buddhist
teachings
in the third line
you don't understand the buddha's
teachings
and
i don't know
i got this picture for you guys
these are three guys with blindfolds on
okay and these are the guys who think
they have wrong ideas about identity or
self-existence and they're kind of
wandering around in the dark
and i just wanted you to see this
picture
because i want you to appreciate
why
does nagarjuna keep saying
they don't get it what the buddha said
historically why do you think he might
be hung up on this point for a hundred
dollars
historically historically
my mother
why does he keep coming back to this
theme of you don't get what the buddha
thought
yeah good you got 50 bucks so far
said there was another system that
contradicted
was popular for how long for 50. for the
second year
700 years
yeah i'll be done with 700 years
people misunderstood they quoted buddha
they memorized buddha they could
memorize they could recite all those
books and according to nick's text
professor nick's text
buddha kept you know the abi dharma
sutras
they also describe emptiness okay
nagajana proves in the 60 verses
that that
the original sutras that we call
hinayana also talked about emptiness he
proves it okay so imagine how frustrated
it is to garjana
he's bucking
700 years of misunderstandings he's
trying to stand up in front of a 700
year tidal wave you know by himself you
know hey guys it's all wrong
so he has to keep going back to the
scriptures and saying
you don't get it you guys just don't get
it you know that's not what he meant
okay got it
can't you hear 700 years of frustration
in his voice i don't know
all right
that's the blindfold i'm supposed to
remind you
uh now we shift to a major major topic
in buddhism extremely important
and i'm sorry it's halfway through the
last class for today because everyone's
tired but here we go
uh
very important
very important for the two husbands in
the kitchen
okay
uh chum day
bhagavan the buddha said
uh he understood kimba the buddha
understood the difference between
the real
and the unreal okay
the buddha understood the difference
between real and unreal okay the husband
in the kitchen is real
and the husband in the kitchen was
unreal he understood the difference and
in a book called
personal advices to katyayana this is
one of his
favorite disciples okay
katyana is very
very important in
in the sutras about the wheel of life
uh he he's there when they first paint
the wheel of life he then he comes home
and tells the story
okay so anyway uh
buddha gave private advices to kathy and
i went looking for them
you find some but they're not clear okay
the buddha denied that things could
exist and the buddha also denied that
things could not exist
okay the buddha denied that things exist
and he denied that things can't exist
okay all right
and that's really a big negotiating very
very important
it's very helpful in the two husbands in
the kitchen
for a hundred dollars
where's the
deny something exist
and deny that something doesn't exist in
the kitchen
you gotta get both to get the hundred
dollars
what's what does exist in the kitchen
and what doesn't exist in the kitchen
the husband you created exists
yeah and the husband is not your fault
don't exist to say that the one that
don't exist does exist is called the
extreme of existing
and to say that the one who
does exist doesn't exist
is called the extreme of not existing
you went too far
there's oh if the kitchen if the husband
in the kitchen is not my fault he don't
exist sorry
if the husband in the kitchen is not his
fault he don't exist at all
got it
and because the husband in the kitchen
is my fault he does exist
so their husband exists and doesn't
exist at the same time to deny that he
exists is a problem
to deny that the husband who's your
fault exists is wrong
and to deny that there's any husband in
the kitchen at all is also wrong
got it two extremes we call falling off
a cliff in fact the picture here
is of a bridge
uh shredding i i was trying to find one
in there i got lucky you know
you this is called middle way
and you're trying to thread your way
through
doesn't exist and does exist okay if you
think the husband who's not your fault
does exist you fell off one side if you
think there's no husband at all
then you fell off the other side okay
and here is the great reference to that
idea in all of buddhist scripture it's
here
okay yay
okay which means a good place to throw
in a sanskrit lesson
and i researched
the extreme of saying he exists
from his own side
and the extremists saying he doesn't
exist at all
okay so those have special technical
terms in buddhism
which is called yep
okay
you
from his side and not because i yell at
my kid
that's called
by the way i'm really thinking the next
book i write i am going to write that
two husbands sutra
okay so
buddha
but it's called bhutakoti say bhutakoti
botakoti
bhutakoti
extreme or cliff okay kochi means cliff
or extreme
uh koti also means 10 million but that's
a different thing
okay
uh okay
so boo boo means to be
and it came from you in indo-european
it's called bu
and we get the words be
build where is the sensement lesson
oh i'm sorry i must have let you know
oopsie
uh build b build and physics comes from
that
physics of the flow
in physics comes from
uh koti i couldn't find much except cut
which means angle sharp angle something
you fall off
and
kotika
is the move in music for thirty dollars
mushi
yeah uh what do you call
permutations yeah four permutations okay
this is 20 bucks for that answer it
means uh for uh
it's like a you're on a table with four
engines
four possible combinations okay kochi
that's called kotika
all right good
then the opposite is
what's the opposite
christina of bhutakurti
okay
which means the extreme of thinking if
he's not coming from his side he doesn't
exist in the kitchen
which is also another extreme
which of those two extremes is learned
and which of those two extremes is
inherent
in people
uh the classical answer okay obviously
you can chew on it
is that the extreme of saying
he doesn't exist at all
comes from a bad explanation of
emptiness
that's all that is normally learned
you know if he's not what i thought he
was then he doesn't exist at all
is is
is most often said by people who didn't
understand what emptiness means
all right here we go let's do some more
[Music]
this is two separate thoughts and they
are wrong they're our own system
uh kelter
if any entity existed to some nature of
its own which means the kind of identity
we've been talking about all right
then
mainly min euro it could never change
okay if it's identity was inherent it
could never change to something else
which means it could never stop because
that's also changing
okay so if if things had a
an identity of their own
because the identity is permanent the
thing could never stop
because it had a permanent identity
it's very interesting idea okay
and he says
it would be like namco mean dipper
what's a dipper thing do you remember
uh to
obscure
to cover okay
then uh
he says tony llama says
what's that what's
four kinds of space right
you gotta say empty space never changes
he says then everything
if things had identities
then because the identities never
changed
those things could never change because
if they changed they would lose their
identity
and then that also means if the identity
lasts forever the thing would have to
last forever and it would be like empty
space which lasts forever whether the
earth is in that space whether the
planet earth is in that space
or whether you destroy the planet earth
the space is always going to be there
mod dip means
it's open and cannot be obstructed okay
it's not like a box it's like the space
okay so if the
identity of a thing never changed the
thing would last forever
if the identity of thing did change then
that's not much of an identity is it
if fire could get cold then
then what's the use of having an
identity okay got it
okay
[Music]
then the other guy comes and oh my god
first he puts us and then he puts the
other guy and he doesn't tell us he's
switching
okay here we go
if the milk's nature
could never change
then where did the yogurt come from
if the milk's nature
could never change
then
who who turned into milk i don't turn
into yogurt sorry
if the milk's nature could never change
then who turned into yogurt okay
and uh
then we say
if the
milks
if the male could have in nature
then what changes
okay it's called ripa gotso ribagotsu
means parallel reasoning i'll say it
again
he says
uh
sorry i gotta look at it
if things don't have a nature of their
own
then
how can you say it changed into
something else
if milk doesn't have a nature how can
you say the milk turned into yogurt
if the milk doesn't have a certain
identity how can you say it changed
to something else if
if you don't have a driver's license to
start with how can you say you got a
fake driver's license
how's that
okay
nah that's the other guy and then we say
no you don't get it if it does have an
identity
then it couldn't change
[Music]
don't tell me it couldn't change if it
didn't have an identity which is his
argument
if it's not something how can i change
and we say no you don't get it if it is
something how can it change
okay
got it
cute
confusing halfway through the second
half we switched to us
thanks
all right and uh
i don't know i forget why i put a
sculptor here
yeah i mean the idea is uh could you
change something which was unchangeable
or something like that you know
okay all right here we go
don't worry we're getting there
the next verse is even more famous than
the last ones i told you were famous
okay this is the super famous verse
shepard
if you think things exist you are
falling into the extreme of thinking
that things can never change
if you think that things don't exist you
are falling into the extreme of thinking
things never started
therefore
you
those
those of you who are
masters should stay in the middle
and there's middleweight okay
what's the nickname of wisdom
what's in yeah middleweight
madhyamaka
that's the nickname of prasna
where do you see that nickname used for
a hundred dollars
[Music]
did not call his book entering wisdom
he called it empty in the middle way
but that middle way
is called madhyamaka shastra
the commentary on the memory okay
all right so here it is
if you think things exist
then they could never change if you
think things don't exist
then you're a nihilist
okay therefore
real wise men and women
should stay somewhere between those two
you should stay between those two
what's that mean in the kitchen for
three hundred dollars
go slow go slow this is a lot of money
what's it where's the middle way in the
kitchen when you understand that
is because
you yell at your kids
okay
and therefore that's that's exists what
doesn't exist in the kitchen
because i didn't do anything that i
didn't do any husband don't exist yeah
so stay between those two places okay
got it
three hundred dollars
she's taking out the dinner party
okay
okay and he expands on the meaning of
unchanging
and
never starting by the way
these two extremes
unchanging
and discontinuing
these two extremes are described as the
results of certain opinions
they're always described as the result
of certain opinions
if the husband
was coming from
[Music]
his own son
he could never change dakba okay
and what's the other one
uh
chipper
if he
i guess if he is coming
oh if if if he's not coming from his own
side he can't exist
then he just
stopped
okay got it
okay
all right and
i have a special picture i made for you
guys
the middle way too
[Music]
that to husband
thank you
so
if you think he exists from his own side
you fell off the right side of the
bridge
if you think if he doesn't come from his
own side he can't exist you fell off the
left side of the bridge and if you stay
in the middle way
you have this happy relationship
[Music]
okay
oh i'm so sorry that's the last picture
of the class okay so let's summarize um
what was the name of this chapter
we were discussing identity okay could a
thing
could something have an identity of its
own
and and we decided it could
not have an identity in its own
because even those
characteristics of things like the heat
of fire that seem to be in the fire are
coming from us
that's the bottom line okay so there is
no natural identity to anything
hey okay oh what i mean about medicine
buddha mantras
yeah suppose you had a bad motivation
and you didn't mess up
what would happen then that's a sign of
the
of the identity of the mantra
does it have an identity of being
beneficial
no if you say those mantras like with a
competitive attitude
then they could hurt somebody right cool
that's the emptiness of the monkeys
they don't have an
identity of their own
cool see you next time